This is one of the many
videos that arose
out of my research for my new book,
How Not to Age.
In this video and the next,
we're going to be talking about
the amount of influence
genetics has on longevity.
"Is Longevity Genetic?"
It has long been said that
the best hope for a long life
is to choose your parents
wisely.
After all, doesn't longevity
just run in the family?
Centenarians are people
who live to be at least 100,
and their siblings
are certainly more likely
to become centenarians
themselves,
and the parents of centenarians
have been found to be
more likely to have lived
to at least 90 years old.
On the other hand,
the lifespans of spouses
sometimes correlate as much,
or even more than,
those of genetic relatives.
Your partner may have as much
of an impact as your parent.
After all, genes aren't the only
things that get passed down.
Perhaps Grandma's
healthy recipes
or even a lifelong
love of running
runs in the family, too.
To tease out
the role of genetics,
researchers turn
to twin studies,
comparing difference between
identical twins
and fraternal twins.
For example, imagine
you're trying to determine
the role of genetics
in cancer--
the role played by genes,
versus other factors
that we may have control over.
Since identical twins share
100 percent of their genes,
whereas, on average, regular
twins only share 50 percent,
if genes play a large role,
then you'd expect that identical
twins would be more likely
to share the same fate
than fraternal twins, right?
If there were no difference
in the chances
that both sets of twins
got the same disease,
then it would appear
there's no genetic contribution.
It turns out that
the overwhelming contributor
to the causation of cancer
is not genetics,
but rather,
what we're exposed to.
Primary genetic factors
may only account
for 5 to 10 percent
of all cancers.
The BRCA genes popularized
by Angelina Jolie, for example,
may account for as little as
2 percent of breast cancers.
If one identical twin
gets breast cancer,
the likelihood the other
will too is only 13 percent,
despite having
essentially identical DNA.
Now, that's higher
than shared rates
among nonidentical twin women,
so there is a genetic component,
but genes only appear
to make a minor contribution
to cancer risk.
This is consistent with
the rates of common cancers
profoundly differing by as much
as 200-fold around the world.
What do twin studies have to say
about the heritability
of lifespan?
Based on a study
of thousands of twin pairs,
the heritability of longevity
was 26 percent for men
and 23 percent for women.
Subsequent twin studies have
arrived at a similar estimate:
approximately 25 percent
of our lifespan is determined
by our genetic differences,
which means
how we live our lives
may determine
the bulk of our destiny.
Estimates using other methods
tend to fall in
the 15 to 30 percent range.
For example, an analysis
of millions of family trees
from 86 million public profiles
in an online genealogy database
led to an estimate
of 16 percent,
though due to so-called
"assortative mating,"
meaning the fact that
we tend to pair up with mates
similar to ourselves,
rather than at random,
that may actually be
an overestimate.
Chosen partners often have
similar lifestyles,
so some of that
16 percent estimate
may have been influenced
by families sharing
similar diets
and healthy habits,
and not exclusively their genes.
Taking that into account,
the actual heritability
of lifespan may even be
well below 10 percent.
To leverage
the lifespan leeway we have
beyond the relatively small
genetic component,
we must first understand
the aging pathways
that account for
the nine hallmarks of aging.
The term "anti-aging" has been
much abused in popular culture,
attached to all manner
of unproven products
and procedures.
The term should probably
be reserved for things
that can delay or reverse aging
through the targeting
of one or more of the
established aging mechanisms.
In a landmark paper
cited nearly 7,000 times
in the biomedical literature,
"The Hallmarks of Aging"
delineates nine
common denominators
of the aging process.
They are Genomic Instability,
the accumulation of DNA damage.
Telomere Attrition,
the loss of the protective caps
at the end of our DNA strands.
Epigenetic Alterations,
changes in the way
our genes are expressed.
Loss of Proteostasis,
the buildup
of misfolded proteins.
Deregulated Nutrient Sensing,
metabolic alterations
particularly sensitive to diet.
Mitochondrial Dysfunction,
the declining efficiency
of our cellular power plants,
Cellular Senescence,
the arrest of cell replication.
Stem Cell Exhaustion,
the loss of the potential
of our tissues to regenerate,
and Altered
Intercellular Communication,
the rise in
proinflammatory signals.
I'm going to be
covering each of them,
and what we can do to slow,
stop, or reverse each one,
in my upcoming book,
How Not to Age.